Guide to the Alexander Addison Papers, 1786-1803 DAR.1925.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Alexander Addison Papers
1786-c1805
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Addison, Alexander
DAR.1925.06
0.63 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
This collection contains correspondence to Alexander Addison, the president judge of the Fifth District Court of Pennsylvania from 1791 to 1802. His correspondents include Hugh Henry Brackenridge, William Findley and Charles Nisbet. It also contains two letters written by Alexander Addison to Hugh Henry Brackenridge. The bulk of the correspondence discusses political events in the United States and Europe, particularly the Constitutional Convention, Jay and Pinckney Treaties, Indian wars, and the Whiskey Rebellion. The majority of the correspondence has typed transcriptions that are included within the files. Digital reproductions of this collection are available online.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of this collection are available online.
Biography
The last quarter of the eighteenth century saw the formation of the United States government after the end of the Revolutionary War. Constitutional ratification, following the 1787 Constitutional Convention, was a tremendously contentious issue, as were issues of foreign policy surrounding the 1795 Jay Treaty with Britain, the 1796 Pinckney Treaty with Spain, and the Treaty of Tripoli. Westward expansion created significant legal questions about land ownership, development, and taxation, while Indian wars raged from the 1780s to the 1790s. Unrest over the excise tax on whiskey that swept through the American frontier came to a head in western Pennsylvania in 1794.
The papers of Alexander Addison address most of these major happenings in post-revolutionary America. Born in Scotland, Addison (1758-1807) received his Master of Arts from Aberdeen University at age nineteen. He subsequently trained as a minister, and was admitted by the Presbytery of Aberlowe in 1781. However, upon immigrating to the newly independent America in 1785, the Redstone Presbytery in western Pennsylvania refused to license Addison as a minister. As an alternative, he apprenticed as a lawyer and was later admitted to the Washington County, Pennsylvania, bar in 1787. Addison started his legal career as an itinerant lawyer. When Addison began practicing law, many of the judges and justices of the peace were men without formal education in law who were appointed by the state executive. However, the 1790 State Constitution required each district court to be headed by a President Judge educated in the law. In 1791, Addison was appointed the president judge of the Fifth Judicial District of Pennsylvania, which included all of western Pennsylvania. For thirteen years Addison presided over the nascent Fifth District when both state and federal laws were being written and little legal precedent existed.
During the Whiskey Rebellion, Addison upheld the authority of state and federal law. In 1802, he was impeached from the bench as a result of ongoing and politically motivated conflict with fellow Justice John B. C. Lucas. Addison published various political tracts many of which are now available in digitized form. His papers trace extended correspondence with three notable men of Pennsylvania, each highlighting a different type of relationship and set of i nterests and issues detailed below. Addison died in 1807.
Charles Nisbet (1736-1803) was born in Scotland and educated at the University of Edinburgh and Divinity Hall. He served as a minister for various Scottish congregations. He was recruited by Dickenson College, in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, and became Principal there on July 5, 1785. A respected scholar, Nisbet was deeply committed to traditional Scottish-style university education and the ministry. He was consistently disappointed with what he viewed as an American disrespect for authority and tradition.
William Findley (1741/1742-1821) immigrated to Philadelphia in 1763. He was politically active at the state and federal level. Between 1789 and 1791 he variously served Pennsylvania in the General Assembly, the State Supreme Executive Council, the State House of Representatives, and the State Constitutional Convention. For the duration of 1791 through 1799 he served as an Anti-Administration and later as a Republican candidate in the second through fourth congresses. During this time, Findley worked to quiet the Whiskey Rebellion. Following his time as a federal congressman, Findley served in the Pennsylvania State Senate from 1799 to 1802. He was successfully elected back to the House of Representatives, as a Republican, in the eighth through fourteenth Congresses.
Hugh Henry Brackenridge (1748-1816) was a well-known lawyer, newspaper publisher and political agitator in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Born in York County, Pennsylvania, he attended college and Divinity School at Princeton. Following his service as a chaplain in the Revolutionary War, he moved to Pittsburgh and was admitted to the Allegheny Country Bar with Alexander Addison and John Woods. After his mixed role in the Whiskey Rebellion and a failed U.S. congressional race against Albert Gallatin, he was appointed to the Pennsylvania Supreme Court. Throughout his life, Brackenridge wrote and published the Pittsburgh Gazette, and penned a number of books, most notably his multiple editions of Modern Chivalry. He started his family in Pittsburgh and had four children, Henry Marie who went on to fame in government service, Cornelia, William, and Alexander Brackenridge. He later moved to Carlisle, Pennsylvania, where he continued to conduct affairs in Pittsburgh until his death.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection of correspondence contains long runs of letters from newspaper publisher Hugh Henry Brackenridge and from the Reverend Charles Nisbet of Dickinson College, and a short run of letters from Congressman William Findley. Addison, Brackenridge, Nisbet and Findley were all educated men of Pennsylvania. To Addison, Brackenridge was a fellow lawyer and writer. Nisbet was Addison's friend and a fellow Scottish theologian. Findley's relationship to Addison is less clear, although they both worked to quiet the Whiskey Rebellion. The bulk of the correspondence relates to the time and place in which they were written. All correspondents mention constitution ratification and early congressional events. Brackenridge writes repeatedly about the Jay Treaty and Pinckney Treaty. Brackenridge also references events surrounding the Whiskey Rebellion, and writes about his political enemy, Albert Gallatin, a federalist and foil to Alexander Hamilton's fiscal policy. Brackenridge provides editorial feedback on Addison's political tracts and essays. Findley's few letters detail events in the House of Representatives. Nisbet's letters are the most colorful, and touch upon the broadest range of domestic and foreign issues, most notably his openly sarcastic hostility towards post-revolutionary politics, both American and French. Nisbet also corresponds extensively with Addison about deeply personal problems related to Nisbet's alcoholic son.
Names of people and events that are inferred, rather than explicitly stated in the correspondence, are bracketed in the item level scope content notes. The majority of the correspondence includes typed transcriptions, which are filed with the original letters. Address information within the correspondence varies and is noted at the item level when known.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into series by correspondent. Series IV contains two small silhouette drawings not directly related to the correspondence.
Missing Title
Series I. Correspondence between Hugh Henry Brackenridge and Alexander Addison, 1796-1798
Series II. Correspondence between William Findley and Alexander Addison, 1791-1794
Series III. Correspondence between Charles Nisbet and Alexander Addison, 1786-1803
Series IV. Miscellaneous
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Part of the original donation of William M. Darlington's family library to the University of Pittsburgh in 1918 and 1925 by his daughters, Edith Darlington Ammon and Mary Carson Darlington.
The Manuscript fragment contained in Folder 90, was purchased by the University Library System in 2016.
Previous Citation
Alexander Addison Papers, 1786-1803, DAR.1925.06, Darlington Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Custodial History
This collection was located in the Darlington Memorial Library in the University's Cathedral of Learning until 2007 when it was moved to the ULS Archives Service Center for processing, storage, preservation and service. However, it remains in the custodianship of the ULS Special Collections Department.
Related Materials
Many digitized copies of Alexander Addison's published works are available in the Early American Imprints, Series I: Evans, 1639-1800 database indexed by Newsbank, Inc., in their Archive of Americana.
Hugh Henry Brackenridge and Andrew Watson Papers, 1784-1827, DAR.1925.04, Darlington Collection, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Bibliography
Bell, Albert H. Memoirs of the Bench and Bar of Westmoreland County. Batvia, NY: The Batvia Time Publishing Company, 1925.
History of Allegheny County, Pennsylvania. Chicago: A. Warner Co., 1889.
Morgan, James Henry. Dickenson College The History of One Hundred and Fifty Years 1783-1933. Carlisle, PA: Mount Pleasant Press J. Horace McFarland Company, 1933.
Biographical Directory of the United States Congress 1774-2005. Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office, 2005.
Washington County (Pa.); Philadelphia (Pa.); Carlisle (Pa.); Indians of North America -- Wars -- 1750-1815; Haiti -- History -- Revolution, 1791-1804; Haiti; Slavery -- Haiti -- Insurrections, etc.; United States -- History -- Constitutiional period, 1789-1809; San Lorenzo Treaty, 1795; Politics; Whiskey Rebellion, Pa., 1794; Government; Lawyers -- Pennsylvania -- Correspondence; Personal papers; France -- History -- Consulate and First Empire, 1799-1815; France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799; Drawings (Visual works); Correspondence; Findley, William -- Correspondence; Nisbet, Charles -- Correspondence; Addison, Alexander -- Correspondence; Gallatin, Albert -- Correspondence; Brackenridge, H. H. (Hugh Henry) -- Correspondence; United States. Constitutional Convention (1787); United States. Congress. House; Great Britain. Treaties, etc.. United States, 1794 Nov. 19
- Correspondence between Hugh Henry Brackenridge and Alexander Addison, 1796-1798; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  It is likely that Brackenridge writes from Pittsburgh to Addison in Westmoreland County. This run of letters is a political discussion between two legal and literary peers. Addison published a number of political works from 1796 to 1798. Brackenridge comments on a variety of political issues, including his opposition to the Jay Treaty with Britain and the Monroe-Pinckney Treaty with Spain, as well as events related to the Whiskey Rebellion. Also, Brackenridge makes references to Albert Gallatin, who defeated him in the 1795 congressional race. Brackenridge discusses Addison's political writings as both an editor and as a fellow writer. Conflict arose between the two men in September 1798 when Brackenridge published a piece in the Pittsburgh Gazette that affected Addison personally, professionally and politically. In 1802, Brackenridge's friend, John B. C. Lucas, was appointed to the Fifth District court. Conflict between Lucas and Addison led to Addison's subsequent impeachment.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, January 7, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    In this letter, Brackenridge writes about legal cases and Judge Smith.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, February 15, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Brackenridge discusses a letter of [Jean] Fauchet and a proposed treaty. He mentions various Pennsylvania judges and cases in which he is involved. Halfway through the letter, Brackenridge apologizes for his worse than average handwriting in the first part of the letter and admits to writing it late at night after drinking.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, April 26, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Brackenridge makes editorial comments about an article Addison has drafted for Brackenridge's Pittsburgh Gazette regarding the [Pinckney] Treaty. He encourages Addison to sign the article to give it greater weight in public debate.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, April 27, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Brackenridge writes to Addison to persuade him to publish a piece of writing. He goes on to comment on the conflict in the [presidential] cabinet concerning French and Spanish diplomatic actions.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, April 30, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    [It is possible this letter is a copy.] This letter discusses plans to organize a meeting to protest the Spanish Treaty [Pinckney Treaty] and British Treaty [Jay Treaty] in support of a petition opposing [congressional] appropriations [for the British Treaty]. Brackenridge also discusses W. Findley, W. Woodbridge, Cardinal McMillan, and Gallatin.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, May 20, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    This letter relates to Brackenridge's previous correspondence from April 30, 1796. In it, Brackenridge plans to publish a work of Addison's related to the ongoing treaty negotiations abroad.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, May 1796 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Brackenridge makes editorial comments on one of Addison's essays. He has apparently shared Addison's essay with John Lucas, who agreed with Gallatin and disagreed with Addison, and Dr. Stephenson. Brackenridge also writes that the appropriation they had petitioned against has gone through. Brackenridge discusses himself and Addison as writers, his desire to write a history of America, and his alienation from both political parties.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, June 29, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Brackenridge asks Addison to settle some business affairs on his behalf and also requests that he purchase some books. Additionally, he refers a merchant to Addison for legal advice.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, July 1, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    This is an addendum to a previous letter requesting additional legal texts. Brackenridge also refers to a colleague's case in Uniontown, Pennsylvania, and writes of distributing Addison's publication.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, November 22, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Brackenridge clarifies a conversation Addison had with John Lucas about an article in the Pittsburgh Gazette. He also discusses General Washington and the Miller's Run Lands and talks of elections in a postscript.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, April 7, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    In this brief letter, Brackenridge critiques Addison's draft and jokes about his negligent treatment of Addison's, and his own, drafts.
  - Alexander Addison to Hugh Henry Brackenridge, September 3, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    In his letter, Addison calls Brackenridge to task for an article he published in the Gazette that embarrassed Addison professionally.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, September 3, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    This is a Brackenridge's response to Addison's letter of September 3, 1798. In the postscript, Brackenridge asks for an interview.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, September 3, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Brackenridge writes to rescind his request for an interview because Addison may soon hear a case against him.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, September 1798 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    In this letter, Brackenridge makes reference to a previous letter and some publishing issues. He also refers to his conflict with Addison and Wood.
  - Alexander Addison to Hugh Henry Brackenridge, September 4, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Addison writes to Brackenridge confirming receipt of his two letters. He suggests that Brackenridge apologize to the court for publishing comments that made it look foolish and asks permission to show Brackenridge's letters to the court. He also accepts Brackenridge's offer of an interview.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, September 1798 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Brackenridge gives Addison permission to show his letter to the court.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    In this fragment, Brackenridge discusses political developments between the French and the Spanish. He also writes with news of settlers in Detroit, a visit from Sebastion [sic] and Powers, and a letter from Mr. Ross predicting war between Spain and Britain.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Brackenridge opens the letter satirizing a French tutor he knows, and the French nobility in exile. He goes on to counter an argument made by Gallatin, and published by Brown, concerning treaties. He briefly describes Fergus Ferguson.
  - Hugh Henry Brackenridge to Alexander Addison, undated. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Brackenridge discusses Madison's speech. Brackenridge also mentions the petition he co-authored with Addison opposing the [Pinckney] treaty, suggesting that Gallatin and Findley found the petition treasonous.
- Correspondence from William Findley and Alexander Addison, 1791-1794; II.
  Findley writes from Philadelphia to Addison in Washington County. The majority of this correspondence concerns events in the House of Representatives, in which Findley served as an Anti-Administrative and Republican congressman from 1791-1799 in the second through fifth congresses. Findley also served in the Pennsylvania State House of Representatives in 1791.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, December 13, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Findley discusses his experience as a congressman in the first session of the second Congress of the United States, and his work on a bill 'fixing representation' addresses current problems with representation in the Senate. He also mentions the poor state of the militia, future congressional candidate, Mr. Woods, and the Revolution in France.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, January 9, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Findley thanks Addison for his letter and writes that he has published some extracts from it. He makes observations about the failure of the Representation Bill and debate over the Post Office Bill. He vents his frustrations about getting work done in Congress and trouble with record keeping of proceedings. A postscript discusses Congressional inability to pass measures on the protection of the frontier and thanks Addison for sending along a packet of clippings about Mr. Woods.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, February 10, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Findley writes to inform Addison that the bill to raise the army to protect the frontier was rejected because a new commander had not yet been approved. Additionally, Findley acknowledges the problem with [Northwest] Indian Wars.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, November 30, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Findley's letter discusses postal restrictions and rates. He also mentions Claypole and Cal Biddle.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, December 20, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Findley's letter discusses how the British do not fulfill their treaty and mentions paying the militia troops in the recruit service.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, March 28, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Findley writes that he has been ill and has not written Addison sooner because he feels more comfortable receiving news about Washington and Fayette counties from Representatives of those areas. He discusses tension between his party and Hamilton, who he believes is setting up a monarchical administration. Findley also discusses the impact of French and British hostilities on American trade routes.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, April 30, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Findley discusses the senate's rejection of the prohibitory bill and that it was probably Mr. Hamilton's plan. Also how the senate rejected the bill for encouraging the recruiting service.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, November 28, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Findley discusses the consideration to authorize the president to allow to keep 2,000 men in our county. He also wishes to know the stability of Addison's county and the militia they kept.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, January 9, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Findley states how he believes the Constitution was violated and the Judiciary Authority abused due to the Senate expelling the western members. Findley wishes that all expelled members would return if they we not offended.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, January 3, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Findley describe how most believe that the news of the French defeat in Germany is a fabrication to help quite the English at home from rioting. Also he mentions talking with Mr. Brackenridge.
  - William Findley to Alexander Addison, May 6, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Correspondence from Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, 1786-1803; III.
  Nisbet wrote from his home in Carlisle, Pennsylvania to Addison at his residence in Washington County, Pennsylvania. His letters from 1786 to 1795 are steeped in Nisbet's colorfully articulated and overwhelmingly negative view of revolutionary politics. Nisbet's common complaint that the world had gone "liberty-mad" extends to American politics, Revolutionary and post-revolutionary France, and his professional frustrations as Principal of Dickenson College. Some of Nisbet's comments about the French may be related to John B. C. Lucas, the French-born Fifth District judge whose actions precipitated Addison's impeachment in 1802. Nisbet critiques them all with a sense of humor. A number of significant events are addressed in the letters, including; the progress of the French Revolution and its impact on Europe and the Americas; the Northwest Indian War led by General "Mad" Anthony Wayne; the Chickamauga Wars with a branch of the Cherokee Nation in the South; African slave revolts in the French Caribbean; unproven bribery allegations against Secretary of State Edmund Randolph; the early Federal Congresses; and the Whiskey Rebellion. Nisbet revels in pointing out hypocrisy and inconsistency in American and French politics. However, the correspondence takes a very personal turn in 1797 when Nisbet's son moves to Washington County to live with Addison. Between 1797 and his death in 1803, Nisbet and his wife tried desperately, with Addison's help, to deal with their son's descent into alcoholism and debt.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, January 26, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Nisbet confirms the receipt of Addison's letter and acknowledges Addison's relocation to Pittsburgh. He makes negative comments about the frontier, the average pioneer, and the threat of Indian war. He discusses news from abroad, especially the threat of Algerines [Algerian pirates]. Addison also disparages Spanish civilization and encourages alliances between government and clergy.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, May 26, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Nisbet describe the neighboring Indians and their unwillingness to concede tracts of land or to keep treaties. He realizes that they can not continue communicate with the Indians this way and fears an insurgence of Indiana to come in the summer.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, October 21, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 34)